Exploring data in a programming environment that shows the source code, increases transparency,
reproducibility and empowers users to ask critical questions. But can we make those features accessible to non-programmers?
The Gamma is a simple text based data exploration environment that allows
non-experts to explore data from a wide range of data sources using iterative prompting
a simple, easy to learn interactional principle. Using iterative prompting data,
analysts can construct complete data exploration scripts by repeatedly selecting one of several offered options from an auto-complete list.
Iterative prompting turns auto-complete from a programmer assistance tool into an end-user programming mechanism.
It can be used to access a wide range of data sources in a uniform way.
This includes querying tabular data, retrieving data from data cubes and exploring the structure of graph databases.
Iterative prompting lowers the barrier to entry for programmatic data exploration.
In a study evaluating the first experience of using the Gamma, 12 out of 13 non-programmers completed a non-trivial data exploration task,
half of them without any assistance. To quote a participant from our study,
"For somebody who does not do coding or programming, this does not feel that daunting."